now that we have seen what dram looks
like let's briefly look at how to
connect the dram to the processor so we
have our processor it sends its requests
to level one cach which sends its misses
and write back requests to the larger
level two cache which might send its
misses and write back request to an even
larger level three cache and let's say
that these are all on our processor chip
now what happens is the misses and the
write back requests from the L3 cache
would be made over an external
connection so we need processor pins
here and
traditionally this data would go over
what is called a front side bus now you
want to design the processor chip so
that you can connect it to many possible
memories so you don't design the front
side bus such that it supplies the row
address and the column address and so on
to the memory chips what you have
instead is another chip that contains
the memory controller and that memory
controller will have what's called a
memory Channel connecting it to a data
module and over this channel it will
issue things like open a row read
something get the data write something
Supply the data close a row open another
one and so on and it will usually have
more than one such memory channel so the
memory latency as seen by the level
three cache is not only the access time
of the memory array here it includes
sending the request over a front side
bus having the memory controller figure
it out sending the Page open to the
appropriate Dam sending a request to
read supplying the column addresses and
everything getting the data over the
memory Channel know that you have a
level three Cash miss that means you
want a whole Cash Line worth of data to
read so it takes a while to transfer
that data here then the memory
controller reads it from the memory
Channel which usually has one bus
frequency and sends it at a different
data rate over the front side bus to the
processor chip which then puts the line
together and puts it in the L cache so
the latency includes all of this here in
addition to just the memory axis and
this can be a significant part of the
overall memory
latency so recent processor chips
integrate the memory controller which
means that the memory controller is put
on the same chip as the processor and
the caches now we no longer need the
front side bus we can use lots of onchip
wiring to communicate with the onchip
memory controller so this can be plenty
of bandwidth and very very close this
whole thing is something like 2 by 2
cm and then we just send request
directly through the memory channels to
dram so now the procer chip directly
knows how to talk to drams and open
pages and so on which dramatically can
reduce this part of the latency and
because it's not a negligible part of
the overall latency we get our data from
dram a little bit faster actually 10 20
maybe 30% faster than before but the
cost of that
is that now we designed the processor
chip to talk to a specific kind of Dr
and because of that we need a relatively
High degree of standardization of data
modules so that for example when we go
from 2 GB to 4 GB memory modules we
don't have to redesign our whole chip so
the protocols here got a lot more
standardized and uniform and flexible
than before but in exchange we get to
trans data very quickly between the
processor and the memory controller we
can make the memory controller now very
smart and then access memory in a more
efficient way